Previously on
Space Brothers
むった
＜不運に縁がある兄･六太｡
ひびと
栄光の日生まれの弟･日々人は➡
Older brother Mutta is plagued by bad luck.
Born under a lucky star, younger brother Hibito becomes the first Japanese moonwalker.
日本人初のムーンウォーカーと
なった＞
＜その遥か後ろから
月を目指し始めた兄･六太は➡
Older brother Mutta continues on his long quest to the moon,
日々人との約束を胸に
海底での訓練を終え➡
as he trains at the bottom of the ocean, to fulfill his promise to Hibito.
Kenji, Nitta, and Mutta now wait to be assigned to missions.
にった
ケンジや新田と共にミッシｮンへの
アサインを待っている＞
Meanwhile, Hibito struggles to recover from the panic disorder
＜一方 月面での事故の影響で
パニック障害となった日々人は➡
宇宙飛行士として復帰すべく
もがき苦しんでいる＞
that's afflicted him since a lunar accident, to return to active duty.
＜しかし そのことを
六太は まだ知らない＞
However, Mutta still does not know the truth.
Swayed by a profound sadness
My daydreams lay a bouquet at my feet
space brothers
I stand atop a brand new world
Hoping to catch whatever falls out of this unprecedented miracle
They're here yet again
The days I'll spend growing distant from you
I'll have miles to go before I sleep in peace
I can see the faint radiance of hope
It got mixed into your blood one day and hasn't let you go
That's all
My body grows nimbler by the day
And my heart's shedding tears because it can't keep up
But I lost something once I became an adult
My light slumber
I can see the faint radiance of hope
It's mixed into your blood, so I'll never let you go
That's all
My body stands atop a stage that it won't run away from even if it rains
That makes me break out into a sprint, so goodbye
My midnight slumbers
#86 For Tomorrow
なんば
ブフ～｡
うわ～っとっとっと！
Oops!
That was too strong...
出しすぎ出しすぎ｡
If I let the faucet run like this on the moon,
低重力の月で
こんな勢いよく 水出したら…｡
⦅うおおお～！⦆
《飛び散りまくりだろうな》
water would be everywhere.
《水中でも窓からの光だけで
結構 明るいもんだな》
We're underwater, but the light from the windows is still bright.
《ここで こんだけ節電するん
だから月面基地なら尚更…》
Given how we're always conserving energy here, the moon must be even worse.
《いける！このアイデアなら》
This idea should work!
(ケンジ)ムッ君 行くよ～｡
Mu, we're heading out!
おっおう！
O-Okay.
(ﾃﾞｰﾓﾝ)月面望遠鏡を
断念せざるを得なくなり➡
Forced to abandon the lunar telescope,
次にナンバムッタから
このアイデアが出た時➡
Nanba Mutta proposed a new idea,
私は こう感じました｡➡
which clarified it for me.
彼は この海底２０メートルでの
２週間…｡
Of the astronauts living twenty meters below sea level for the past two weeks,
Nanba Mutta was the one person who truly seemed to be on the moon.
(ﾃﾞｰﾓﾝ)他の誰よりも月面にいた｡
(役員)月面に？
Eh? On the moon?
Huh?
(ﾊﾞﾄﾗｰ)ほう｡
どういうこと？
What do you mean?
つまり六太の この案が➡
The proposal submitted by Mutta is an idea that you would expect from an astronaut with actual lunar experience.
実際に月面基地で過ごした
宇宙飛行士が➡
気付いたようなアイデアだと
いうことです｡
ソーラーミラーシステム？➡
A solar mirror system?
そいつが月面望遠鏡の
かわりの案か｡
This is meant to replace the lunar telescope?
そう 部屋に光を
入れたいんだけど➡
Yep.
We could use more light indoors, but Moonbase wouldn't have any windows due to cosmic radiation.
宇宙線を浴びるのを
防ぐために➡
月面基地は窓がないよな｡
まあ 電池式の
バックアップライトは➡
The base has battery-powered backup lighting,
基地内に装備されてる
みたいだけど➡
ここみたいに
電力不足が起こった時➡
but if they have to conserve energy and keep lights off like we have, it gets pretty dark.
照明を消すと基地内は
暗～くなっちまう｡
それで窓のかわりに
太陽光を取り入れる方法がこれだ｡
So, instead of installing windows, we'll capture sunlight with these.
望遠鏡の反射部分に使おうと
思ってたこのパネルと➡
We can use the panels and reflective film meant for the telescope to make three large mirrors
ミラーフィルムで
大きな鏡を３枚作って➡
反射で室内に太陽光を
取り入れるんだ｡
that will reflect sunlight into the base.
入ってきた光を室内に
かくさん
拡散させるための➡
We'll install a ball of mirrors to disperse light throughout the room.
ミラーボールの
ようなものを設置する｡
これなら光は入ってくるけど➡
This way, we'll let sunlight in, while cosmic radiation is kept out by the regolith wall.
宇宙線は覆われたレゴリスの壁で
しっかり防げる｡
す…すごい いいね これ！
節電にもなるし｡
Th-That's great! It's perfect!
We can even save energy!
確かに月なら太陽の動きも
かなりゆるやかだ｡➡
And on the moon, the sun moves much more slowly.
ミラーで光を
とらえ続けるのも簡単だな｡
Keeping the mirrors focused on the sun should be easy enough.
結局 俺ら宇宙飛行士は
月面生活のほとんどを➡
On the moon, we astronauts will spend most of our time inside the base,
基地の中で過ごすわけだし➡
どうせ設備を追加するなら
中を改善したいと思ってな｡
so why not improve the interior, in addition to the exterior?
基地の中が明るいとクルーの
気持ちも明るくなるってもんだ｡
With more light inside, the crew members will be a lot happier.
さあ！太陽をつけるぞ｡
Okay, let's turn on the sun.
基地内に明かりを…！
Let there be light...
in the base.
おお～！成功だよ ムッ君！➡
Hey... It worked, Mu!
室内部分
ちゃんと明るくなってる！
It's brighter inside the base!
《最後のソーラーミラーの案には
…まいったな》
The solar mirror idea really caught me by surprise.
《基地に追加したい新たな
設備という課題を聞いて➡
When they told us to come up with ways to improve the base,
僕は基地の周りに建設するもの
ばかりを思い浮かべてしまった➡
I was thinking of external additions.
だけどムッ君の言う通りだ｡➡
But Mu's absolutely right.
Astronauts will spend most of their time inside.
過ごすのは ほとんど
基地の中だもんな｡➡
実際その現場にいれば➡
Any astronaut with lunar experience would emphasize what's inside the base.
基地内の問題点から
改善しようと思うはず》
《ムッ君は本当に自分が月面に
いるつもりで やってたんだな》
Mu went through this training as though he were really on the moon.
(ﾃﾞｰﾓﾝ)以上 チームⅡの
総評報告を終わります｡
That concludes my review of Team 2.
うむ…｡
どうです？バトラー室長｡
What do you think, Chief Butler?
ナンバムッタの その案が
今 噂になってるんですよ｡➡
Everyone's talking about Nanba Mutta's proposal.
月面基地の設計チームは
もう実現可能とみなして➡
The infrastructure at Moonbase tells us that the proposal is feasible,
この案で企画書を
作る勢いですよ｡
and they're ready to submit a working plan.
な なるほど｡
O-Oh...
ニーモ
私が ひそかに このＮＥＥＭＯ
訓練に期待していた成果を…｡
It appears he produced the result I was secretly hoping for...
(ﾊﾞﾄﾗｰ)突き抜けられたようです｡
...from this NEEMO training.
Florida
ホタテ貝はね ここの穴から➡
Japanese scallops can use this hole to shoot water.
水をジェット噴射みたいに出して
移動するんだよ｡
Right here!
ここから｡ふふ～ん｡
ほう～お～｡
にった
スリー
これが新田率いるチｰムⅢの
月面基地モデルかぁ｡
So this is the Moonbase model that Nitta's Team 3 built.
別に俺が率いてたわけじゃね～よ｡
It isn't like I was in charge.
何これ？
(新田)発射台だ｡
What's this?
A launchpad.
And this?
これは？
(新田)滑走路だ｡リニア式の｡
A mass driver.
へえ～｡
《かかか…勝った～！》
We win!
《プハハハ！２週間も こんなこと
してたの!?新田君たち｡ヒヒヒ》
Nitta's team spent two weeks building this stuff?
素晴らしい｡さすが新田率いる
チームⅢだ｡
Magnificent!
As I'd expect from the Nitta-led Team 3.
お前ら チームⅡのも
見せてくれよ｡
Show me what Team 2 did.
そら やめといた方がいいな｡
That's a bad idea.
Huh?
ショックのあまり
その写真 燃やしたくなるぞ｡
You'll be so shocked, you'll want to burn those pictures.
何!?
What?
Look up there...
ほ～ら ごらんよ｡
海亀さんの体はね➡
The sea turtle's body is designed perfectly!
とっても合理的に
出来てるんだよ｡
う…う～ん！
Mentaiko (Roe)
《もっと突っ込まれても大丈夫な
ように準備しとかないと！》
I need to prepare more shirts that people will notice.
《やっぱりいいなぁ 日本語｡
意味 わかんないけど》
Japanese is awesome... But I don't understand a word.
この形！
I like how this one looks!
No! My stupid hand!
ノー！僕の手のバカ！
次の議題は え～ 日常における
安全の徹底ということで まず➡
On to the next topic...
Ensuring astronaut safety for everyday life.
Risk Management Meeting
First,
２２期飛行士の
スヴ･タキーユがですね➡
we have astronaut Subu Takil, from the 22nd class.
日曜大工で 宇宙船の飾りを➡
One Sunday, he took a spill, putting a model spaceship on his roof.
自宅の屋根に取り付けようと
したところ え～ 転落｡➡
He hurt his back, requiring two weeks for full recovery.
腰を打って全治２週間という
報告がありました｡
Come on...
まったく…大事な宇宙飛行士の
体を一体何だと思ってんのかねえ｡
Don't these astronauts understand how important their bodies are?
これについて どういう対処を
お考えですか｡ヒビト･チェアマン｡
How do you propose we handle the situation, Chairman Hibito?
(南波日々人)ん？…ん～…➡
今後 宇宙船の飾り？
…の取り付けは➡
Tell him that from now on,
when he puts up model spaceships on the roof, he should hire someone else to do it.
業者に委託するように
本人に忠告しといて下さい｡
なるほど！了解です｡
I see... Understood.
はい！こちらも１件
報告を受けてます｡➡
Oh, I also have a situation to report.
２１期飛行士 チャン･テイシーが
趣味のエレキギターを演奏中➡
Chan Tayshi, of the 21st class, was playing his electric guitar when the strap broke.
ストラップが切れたとかで…➡
The guitar fell and broke his foot in the process.
足の甲にギターを落として
ちゅうそくこつ
中足骨骨折｡➡
As a result, he'll need three months to recover, and he'll miss training.
全治３ヶ月ということで 一部訓練
に参加できないという状況です｡
痛そう！足の甲！
Stuff landing on your foot really hurts!
Actually, the guitar he dropped was vintage,
いやぁ それがね 彼が落とした
ギターはヴィンテｰジ物らしくて➡
and the body got scratched.
ボディーにキズが付いちゃって➡
Apparently, that was more painful for him.
こっちの方が痛いよ～！と
言ってたそうです｡
ハハーッハハハハッ！
Man...
《まったく…ｾｰﾌﾃｨｰ･ｽｰﾊﾟｰﾊﾞｲｻﾞｰに
なってから➡
Having become safety supervisor, I spend all my time in these meetings.
こんな会議ばっかだな》
どういう対処をお考えですか
ヒビト･チェアマン｡
How do you propose we deal with this, Chairman Hibito?
Tell him to buy a new strap for his guitar.
新しいストラップを買うように
言って下さい｡
(ｾｰﾌﾃｨｰ･ｽｰﾊﾟｰﾊﾞｲｻﾞｰ)了解！
Understood!
Okay, time for today's training.
よ～し 今日の分 やるか｡
Let's see...
えっと～ レベル６の剣道着と
レベル７の着ぐるみもクリアして｡
I've cleared Level 6: Kendo Gear and Level 7: Mascot Costume.
And last Thursday, I think...
それから先週の木曜だったかな｡
レベル８ バイクのフルフェイス
スタイルに挑戦したら➡
I tried Level 8: Biker with Full-Face Helmet, and experienced a minor attack.
軽い発作が出てしまった｡
とりあえずオリビアに
薬を貰って飲んだら治まった｡
After Olivia gave me some medicine, it let up.
On my next try, I managed to clear the level.
で…その後またトライして
なんとかフルフェイスはクリア｡
Next up is Level 9...
次はレベル９｡
Souvenir Store Spacesuit.
ＮＡＳＡのお土産屋で売ってる
レプリカの宇宙服だ｡
《こいつをクリアできたら…》
If I clear this level,
《残るは あと２つ》
only two levels remain!
Level 10 is a full pressure suit,
《レベル１０で本物の与圧服｡
そして最後に…➡
and after that
船外活動用宇宙服》
comes the EVA spacesuit.
宇宙服なんて 着てて当たり前｡
By now, wearing spacesuits should be second nature.
I'm almost ready to go back...
《あと少しで…戻れる》
Hey, Lowry! Wait up!
(同僚)≪お～い ローリー！
ちょっと待て！≫
(同僚)お前 最近
噂になってるぞ｡
People have been talking about you.
Huh?
ヒビトとコソコソ何かやってる
ってな｡バレてないと思ったか｡
You've been doing something with Hibito privately, right?
Did you think no one noticed?
うっ！あっ…｡
じ…実は…➡
A-Actually...
休み時間とか仕事終わりにね
ヒビトに日本語を教わってるんだ｡
I asked Hibito to teach me Japanese during breaks or after work...
Because I love Japan.
僕 日本好きだから…｡
Is Dr. Olivia also taking lessons?
医師のオリビアもか？
What?!
Th-That's right...
そ そうだよ！
あんまり知られてないけど➡
Most people don't know this, but she's a big fan of Japan!
実は彼女も
超日本ファンなんだよ｡
(同僚)聞いたことねえなあ｡
First I've heard of it.
はっ 白衣の下には日本語の
Ｔシｬツ着てるらしいよ ひそかに｡
Apparently, she even secretly wears Japanese T-shirts under her coat.
(同僚)マジかよ？
Seriously?
You bet.
Okay, I guess.
まぁ いいけどさ…｡
マズイ…｡
Not good...
And so, I told him that you're a big fan of Japan...
という訳で ｵﾘﾋﾞｱも超日本ファン
だって言っちゃったんだ｡
I'm sorry, but you'll have to learn a few phrases.
だから悪いけど 何個か日本語を
覚えといてくれないかなあ｡
それは別に構わないけど…➡
I don't mind,
but you won't be able to keep this secret forever.
そういつまでも隠し通せるもの
でもないと思うわよ｡
あと オリビア
これ 持ってきたから｡
And, Olivia, I brought these for you to wear.
Huh?
I'm supposed to wear these?
(ｵﾘﾋﾞｱ)私がこれ着んの？
お願いだよ！ﾘｱﾘﾃｨｰを
持たせるために｡
Pretty please? We have to make my lie real...
これは何？魚の骨？
What is this? A fishbone?
お～！さすがオリビア！
Ooh... Nice, Olivia!
To pick that one first, you have good sense...
最初に それをチョイスするなんて
センスいいよね｡
It's the perfect Japanese word for you!
まさに君にピッタリの
日本語だよ｡➡
イッツ ビューティフォー！
It's beautiful!
《いや…それじゃ美しいって
いうよりゲジゲじぃだよ…》
Uh, the way it's written, it looks more like a centipede...
ところでヒビト｡
So, Hibito...
How many minutes have you been wearing that?
今着てる そのレプリカ
着てから何分経ったの？
あ…えっと…｡
Uh...
Whoa, forty-two minutes.
あ！４２分だ｡いつのまに｡
That was fast.
やったじゃん ヒビト！
目標の４０分 超えてる！
Way to go, Hibito!
You passed the forty-minute goal!
レベル９クリアだ！
おめでとう｡
You've cleared Level 9!
Congrats!
おめでとう！
まあ レプリカだしね｡
続きは明日｡
Well, it's only a replica.
We'll continue tomorrow.
Next, I finally put on a real pressure suit.
《次はいよいよ…
本物の与圧服だ》
ベッドじゃねえんだ｡
ちょっとそこ どいてくれ アポ｡
That isn't your bed.
Can you move, Apo?
(アポ)ワン！
あ～あ｡
Ah, Mu finished his NEEMO training today...
《あ…そういやムッちゃんの
ＮＥＥＭＯ 今日までか》
《でも しばらくは
フロリダにいるだろうから➡
But he'll probably stay in Florida for a bit, so I have time before he's back.
帰ってくるまでに なんとか…》
[PC]ＮＡＳＡのお土産屋で売ってる
レプリカの宇宙服だ｡
This is the spacesuit replica that they sell in souvenir stores.
《フフッ 笑える》
It's funny.
The box Ivan sent contained a single card.
《イヴァンから送られてきた
荷物の中には➡
１枚のメッセージカードが
入っていた｡そこには➡
It told me to record all of my rehabilitation training.
｢全てのﾘﾊﾋﾞﾘ訓練の様子を 録画
するように｣と書かれていた｡➡
後でまとめて見て楽しむ気だな｡➡
He'll probably watch it later for some laughs.
Or he wants a record of my development to go with his videos of Olga...
あるいは 俺が前進していく様子を
オリガの成長記録みてえに》
《オリガの成長記録
ボリューム２》
"Olga Grows Up," volume 2.
Yes, yes! Wonderful, Olga!
[PC](先生)
そうそう いいわよ オリガ｡
足を高くあげて｡
Keep your leg high.
You're improving!
[PC](先生)上手になってきた！
Coach, look at Olga!
[PC](女生徒)先生 オリガが！
[PC](先生)どうしたの？オリガ！
What's wrong, Olga?
[PC](先生)
オリガ！大丈夫？オリガ！
Olga, are you okay? Olga?
The hasty hare and the slow and steady turtle
Are both headed toward the place they call their goals
We forgot something very important once we grew up
Forget tomorrow, what can I do right now?
But the two of us
Have always remembered
The importance of taking off
The heavy shackles of hesitation
A brand new world
Is always waiting one step ahead of us
Even our failures will give us strength
And that will be the start of a new world
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#87 To the Place Where I Belong
Olga's videos showed her frustration.
＜オリガの成長記録｡そこには➡
彼女のたどった挫折が
映し出されていた＞
Why did she start to dance again?
＜オリガは どうして
また踊りを始めたんだ？＞
Next time on Space Brothers:
"To the Place Where I Belong"
＜オリガ｡もっと踊ってくれ＞
Olga, don't ever stop dancing...